<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Great Brittans mourning garment Giuen to all faithfull sorrowfull subiects at the funerall of Prince Henry.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03018</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13158</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103979</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839721</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839721</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4168</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03018)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4168)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1143:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Great Brittans mourning garment Giuen to all faithfull sorrowfull subiects at the funerall of Prince Henry.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by G. Eld for Arthur Ionson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Great Britans mourning garment.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry Frederick, --  Prince of Wales, 1594-1612 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4168:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4168:1"/>
            <p>GREAT BRITTANS Mourning Garment.</p>
            <p>GIVEN To all faithfull ſorrowfull Subiects at the Funerall Of Prince <hi>HENRY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON. Imprinted by <hi>G. Eld</hi> for <hi>Arthur Ionſon.</hi> 1612.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4168:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4168:2"/>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>To the Honorable Knight, Sir DAVID MVRRAY.</head>
               <head type="sub">AND To the other Nobly diſcended, and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably minded followers of the late deceaſed Prince <hi>HENRY.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ON whom ſhall I theſe funerall notes beſtow,</l>
                  <l>Newly bedeaw'd &amp; hallowed with my teares?</l>
                  <l>But on you chiefly, for your ſecret woe</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The heauieſt burthen of our ſorrow beares;</l>
                  <l>We but as ſtrangers on the ſhore lament,</l>
                  <l>A common ſhip-wracke, but you that did owe</l>
                  <l>Your ſeruice to that golden veſſel (rent)</l>
                  <l>What wonder if your griefes doe ouer-flow?</l>
                  <l>By how much greater your faire fortunes were,</l>
                  <l>The loſſe is ſo much greater you ſuſtaine,</l>
                  <l>We meaner men may our miſchances beare</l>
                  <l>With leſſer trouble, and more equall paine,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet ſpare your teares though you haue cauſe to mone</l>
                  <l>It is not meete you ſhould lament alone.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:3"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>MElpomene,</hi> and all you ſacred brood,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Mnemoſine</hi> with liuing Lawrell crown'd,</l>
                  <l>You that haue fill'd your veins with heauenly foode</l>
                  <l>And ſcorne to pray vpon the barraine ground,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Helpe me theſe Funerall <hi>Anthems</hi> to reſound.</l>
                  <l>For his ſweet ſoule, who liuing lou'd you deere</l>
                  <l>But now is dead, and other Saints hath found,</l>
                  <l>Leauing you to lament his fortunes here.</l>
                  <l>Strow Cypreſſe, and pale Violets on his Tombe,</l>
                  <l>And on his faire Creſt fixe a Crowne of Bayes</l>
                  <l>Immortall, That who'euer there doth come</l>
                  <l>May view the Enſignes of his endleſſe praiſe:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And let ſome Spirit garde the holy Cell,</l>
                  <l>Wherin the bones of that braue <hi>Prince</hi> ſhal dwel.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:3"/>
               <head>III.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YOu gentle ſpirits that turne not your eyes</l>
                  <l>From common griefs, nor are of mettall made</l>
                  <l>Such as theſe Iron Ages do compriſe;</l>
                  <l>Come ſee, wherein our humane glory lies:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>See liuing vertues in death daily fade,</l>
                  <l>Wither'd and waſted in th'vnthankfull graue:</l>
                  <l>For as a flower, or Sommers paſſing ſhade;</l>
                  <l>Such is the hope and fortune worldlings haue:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh noble Prince, thy daies but new begun,</l>
                  <l>And that ſame Enſign long ſince brought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>France</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>Edward</hi> the black-Prince, third <hi>Edwards</hi> Sonne,</l>
                  <l>Being by thee but lately re-aduanc't;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why ſhould ſuch honor into darknes goe,</l>
                  <l>And leaue ſo many friends ſo full of woe?</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:4"/>
               <head>IIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>OH froward <hi>Saturne,</hi> and maleuolent,</l>
                  <l>That euery blooming glory doſt enuie,</l>
                  <l>And with thy froſts doſt nip the buds yet pent</l>
                  <l>In their greene bowers through thy vilde Iealouſie,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And hatefull malice to all liuing things.</l>
                  <l>Why doſt thou ſpread on vs thy diſmall light</l>
                  <l>Couering our faireſt flowers with thy cold wings?</l>
                  <l>How farre art thou vnlike to <hi>Phoebus</hi> bright,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That ioyes to ſee the ſmalleſt bloſſom thriue,</l>
                  <l>And throwes his gentle light on euery thing?</l>
                  <l>But thou, peruerſe, doſt all of life depriue,</l>
                  <l>Man, Beaſt, and Plant thou doſt to ruine bring:</l>
                  <l>Vnlucky Starre, albeit thou thought'ſt him fit</l>
                  <l>To ſtoop to thee, thou might'ſt haue ſpar'd him yet.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:4"/>
               <head>V.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ANd you foule wrinckled deſtinies that do ſit,</l>
                  <l>In darknes to depriue the world of light</l>
                  <l>Making the thread, and ſodaine mangling it,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hrough peeuiſh rancour, and peruerſe deſpight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Your hand appeares in this our Tragedie,</l>
                  <l>The wound we feele, by your ſharp edge was made,</l>
                  <l>That edge which cut the golden twiſt ſo nigh</l>
                  <l>Of our Prince HENRY, who in liueles ſhade</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As yet amaſed of his ſodaine change</l>
                  <l>Lookes for thoſe louing friends whom he lov'd beſt;</l>
                  <l>But when he ſees himſelfe ſo farre eſtrang'd,</l>
                  <l>He Yeilds his ſpirit to eternall reſt:</l>
                  <l>Hard-hearted fates, that him of life depriue,</l>
                  <l>That leaues ſo many mournfull friends aliue.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:5"/>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SAd Melancholy lead me to the Caue</l>
                  <l>Where thy black Incenſe and dim Tapers burne,</l>
                  <l>Let me ſome darke and hollow corner haue,</l>
                  <l>Where deſolate my ſorrowes I may mourne:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And let thy heauieſt Muſick ſoftly ſound</l>
                  <l>Vnto the doleful ſongs that I recite;</l>
                  <l>And euer let this direfull voice rebound</l>
                  <l>Through the vaſt den: Ah dead is <hi>Britans</hi> light;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then if thy heart be with compaſſion mou'd</l>
                  <l>Of my Laments, come reſt thy ſelf by me,</l>
                  <l>And mourne with me, for thou haſt euer lov'd</l>
                  <l>To beare a part in euery Tragedie:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And if to plaints thou wilt inure thy mind,</l>
                  <l>Thou neuer couldſt a fitter ſeaſon finde.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:5"/>
               <head>VII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHo in ſome earthly Paradice hath eſpide,</l>
                  <l>And long time view'd with pleaſure of his eye</l>
                  <l>A well growne Plant, adorn'd on euery ſide</l>
                  <l>With beautious bloſſomes lifted vp on high,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ready when his due ſeaſon ſhall require,</l>
                  <l>To yeild the ſweet fruite of his boaſted flowers,</l>
                  <l>But all on ſodaine with heauens liquid fire</l>
                  <l>Is blaſted, and on earth vntimely powers,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His vnripe glorie by his Fate preuented:</l>
                  <l>Who ſuch a luckles ſpectacle hath knowne;</l>
                  <l>Let him compare the fortune then preſented</l>
                  <l>Vnto Prince HENRIES Fate, and let him mone</l>
                  <l>That he to leaue all Tropheis now is ſeene,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Creſt of late was honored with, ICH <hi>Dien.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:6"/>
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THey that ſhall ſee Prince HENRIES ſad built Tomb,</l>
                  <l>And think his corps are only ſhrouded there,</l>
                  <l>Erre farre from truth, nor ſeem to vnderſtand</l>
                  <l>How many vertues in that Worthy were.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A thouſand graces with him buried lie,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand Triumphs, and a thouſand loues,</l>
                  <l>With him the life of honor ſeems to die,</l>
                  <l>And that braue troop of Nymphs that from the groues</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Were wont to tread the meaſures through the green;</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>Henries</hi> death into dark caues are fled,</l>
                  <l>Nor euer ſince of mortall eye were ſeene,</l>
                  <l>So that the world reports that they are dead,,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſooth, I know not, but they lov'd him ſo,</l>
                  <l>That 'tis no wonder if they died for woe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:6"/>
               <head>IX.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>EVen as the ſubſtance of a ſhooting ſtar</l>
                  <l>Grown great by Time, now ready with new light</l>
                  <l>Throughout the world to ſpread his glory farre,</l>
                  <l>And emulate the raies of Titan bright,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Soone as the hoped fire hath giuen him powre,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew his glory, and aloft to ſhine,</l>
                  <l>Euen in a moment in the ſelfe-ſame hower,</l>
                  <l>His golden head does downe to earth encline;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And thoſe Illuſtrious beams which lately ſent</l>
                  <l>Such ſtar-like brightnes do to darknes turne,</l>
                  <l>And all his glorious hope ſo quickly ſpent,</l>
                  <l>Leaues but a ſmoaky cloud his end to mourne,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So did Prince HENRY in his glory fall,</l>
                  <l>And left vs nothing but his funerall.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:7"/>
               <head>X</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YOu ſacred Forreſts, and you ſpotles ſtreams</l>
                  <l>That part the flowry medowes with your fall,</l>
                  <l>You water-Nymphes and Ladies of the Tea'ms,</l>
                  <l>And thou dread Thameſis, mother of them all;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With briniſh teares weep in your ſandy Ford:</l>
                  <l>Weep fields, and groues, and you poore Driads weep,</l>
                  <l>The ſodaine Funerall of our Brittiſh Lord,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe eyes are now clos'd vp in iron ſleepe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Both trees, and ſtreams, lament his loſs that lov'd</l>
                  <l>Your ſiluer waters, and wide ſpreading ſhades,</l>
                  <l>But now is farre away from you remoov'd,</l>
                  <l>Vnto a Paradice that neuer fades,</l>
                  <l>There in eternall happineſſe to remaine,</l>
                  <l>But we in ſorrow here, and ceaſleſs paine.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:7"/>
               <head>XI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>OH how vncertaine are the daies of Man?</l>
                  <l>How many dangers vndermine our ioyes?</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe we ſhun the ſtormy Ocean,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſtand agaſt at Cannons fearefull noiſe,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Admit we put <hi>Achilles</hi> Armour on,</l>
                  <l>That neuer could be pierc't by mortall Iron,</l>
                  <l>Or liue enclos'd in towres of braſſe or ſtone,</l>
                  <l>Such as no power of enemy can enuiron.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet are we not ſecure from ſtroake of death,</l>
                  <l>Our foe we nouriſh euen in our breaſts,</l>
                  <l>The venemous diſeaſe that ſtops our breath:</l>
                  <l>Oh learne to caſt out ſuch vngratefull gueſts,</l>
                  <l>Thy fortunes <hi>Henry</hi> had not falne out ſo,</l>
                  <l>If thou hadſt fear'd none but an outward foe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:8"/>
               <head>XII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AWake <hi>Euterpe</hi> my dull drooping Song</l>
                  <l>With thy melodious thundring blaſtes awhile:</l>
                  <l>Helpe thou my fainting fury to prolong,</l>
                  <l>And powre new fire into my frozen ſtile:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then like a bould enchaunter I will call,</l>
                  <l>The mournfull ſhadowes from infernall deepe,</l>
                  <l>They know beſt how t'adorne a Funerall</l>
                  <l>Or what rights doe belong to them that ſleepe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No: Reſt you ghoſts, poſſeſſe your quiet peace,</l>
                  <l>My griefes forbid me to diſturbe the dead,</l>
                  <l>And reſt fond teares, and fruitleſſe Dirges ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>But thou that with thy Trumpet ſhril doſt ſpread</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The praiſe of worthies (oh impartiall fame)</l>
                  <l>Helpe me to celebrate Prince <hi>Henries</hi> name.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:8"/>
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHat grace, what fortuns could our hearts inuent</l>
                  <l>While yet Prince <hi>H.</hi> in his cradel lay?</l>
                  <l>That did not following ioyne in one conſent</l>
                  <l>To make him fortunate to his dying day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Shal I recount the honours with him borne,</l>
                  <l>Which from his worthy Anceſtors were deriu'd?</l>
                  <l>Or thoſe rare vertues, which his mind adorn'd?</l>
                  <l>Or ſhall theſe notes his man-like actions praiſe;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>(Whereof too ſoone our ſenſes are depriu'd?)</l>
                  <l>Or comely geſtures when he pleaſd to grace</l>
                  <l>The Lordly reuells, and a thouſand wayes,</l>
                  <l>The winding meaſure with his ſteps to trace:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, there my Muſe if thou for greefe could ſtay,</l>
                  <l>We might paſſe ouer a long ſummers day.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:9"/>
               <head>XIIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YOw holy Angels, and you powers of light,</l>
                  <l>And you that in old <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome reſt,</l>
                  <l>The glad enioyers of Gods glorious ſight</l>
                  <l>Haue you receiu'd your ſanctified gueſt?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hath <hi>Henry</hi> the Caeleſtiall ſeat obtain'd?</l>
                  <l>Shines he in roabes of immortality?</l>
                  <l>And of his well runne race the crowne now gain'd,</l>
                  <l>Scornes he our earthly Pompe, and Maieſty?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For while his iolly Pilgrimage did laſt,</l>
                  <l>His guiltleſſe hands were free from bloud, and ſtrife;</l>
                  <l>Voide of vaine pride, and as the ſnow new chac't</l>
                  <l>From her high Manſion, was his thread of life,</l>
                  <l>True Chriſtian faith endu'd with conſtant minde,</l>
                  <l>And vnto ſuch the promiſe was aſſign'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:9"/>
               <head>XV.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHereto ſhall I Prince <hi>Henries</hi> life compare?</l>
                  <l>His Infancy eu'n to thoſe beams that ſhine,</l>
                  <l>Before the Sunne vnmaskes his viſage bare</l>
                  <l>Beating the ſhadowes from his goulden eyne.</l>
                  <l>And thoſe bright houres, that with their temperate heat</l>
                  <l>Glad the greene earth, and teach the birds to ſing,</l>
                  <l>And Swaines their ancient Carrols to repeat:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe that preſent his ripe yeeres in their ſpring</l>
                  <l>Thus ſtill with freſh delights, and glory led,</l>
                  <l>Till the ſlow ſhep-heard doth his flock enfould,</l>
                  <l>And th'euening Sun on the dry earth does ſpread</l>
                  <l>New pleaſing light, then ſodainely behold</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Night comes, and chaſes <hi>HENRIES</hi> life away,</l>
                  <l>And makes it like vnto a Sommers day.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:10"/>
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Muſe from whence theſe forward tears ſhold flow</l>
                  <l>Or when our minde of ſecret griefe complaines,</l>
                  <l>Why though vnwilling through our eyes wee ſhow</l>
                  <l>The inward paſſion of our hidden paines.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I know our ſighes are but the cooling ayre,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith our fainting heart we doe ſuſtaine,</l>
                  <l>That els would ſmother in her owne deſpaire,</l>
                  <l>All comfort thankles breathing back againe.</l>
                  <l>But wherefore Nature ſhould in open view,</l>
                  <l>Create two fountaines full of liuing ſource:</l>
                  <l>Whether ſo ſoone as we find cauſe to rue,</l>
                  <l>Our Paſſions make their generall recourſe</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who knowes? vnleſſe thereby we ſhould reueale</l>
                  <l>That our true ſorrowes we ſhould not conceale.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:10"/>
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MOther of heauineſſe yeeld me one requeſt,</l>
                  <l>For many drops vpon thine Altar ſhed,</l>
                  <l>Since thou thy mournful galleries haſt dreſt</l>
                  <l>With carefull monuments of th'untimely dead:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To feed with view of their callamities</l>
                  <l>Thy penſiue humour, and ſelfe-hating ſight,</l>
                  <l>For there <hi>Troyes</hi> Queene in painted languor lies,</l>
                  <l>And forlorne <hi>Dido</hi> rob'd of her delight</l>
                  <l>Kneeles on the burning pile: There <hi>Mauſolus</hi> tomb:</l>
                  <l>There ſtands <hi>Pyrene</hi> wept into a ſpring,</l>
                  <l>And with his loue <hi>Marke Anthony</hi> of Rome,</l>
                  <l>Their griefe in dead imbracements vttering,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Among theſe ſpectacles let a Herſe bee made</l>
                  <l>For wofull HENRY that may neuer fade.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:11"/>
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ONce more <hi>Melpomene</hi> grant thy willing aide,</l>
                  <l>I ſing not now of franticke <hi>Progne's</hi> change,</l>
                  <l>Nor of the boy transform'd into a maide:</l>
                  <l>Nor how the girle did like a Heifar range.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Farre ſadder notes, my ſullen Muſicke yeelds,</l>
                  <l>Farre other dreames afflict my ſad repoſe</l>
                  <l>Of broken Tombes, and of th' <hi>Eliſian</hi> fields,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And of the ſcathfull floulds, <hi>that Dis</hi> encloſe.</l>
                  <l>But let ſuch vaine thoughts vaniſh with my ſleepe,</l>
                  <l>And of Prince <hi>Henries</hi> death now let vs ſing,</l>
                  <l>And teach the Rockes on <hi>Monas</hi> ſhores to weepe,</l>
                  <l>And fright the ſea with their vaſt bellowing:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That <hi>Neptune</hi> hearing of their pitteous cry,</l>
                  <l>May thinke that all the Weſterne world did die.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:11"/>
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THou ſhalt not die Prince HENRY, if my ſongs</l>
                  <l>Hereafter tuned to a higher key</l>
                  <l>Can ſound the honour that to thee belongs,</l>
                  <l>With ſacred murmur of eternity:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With <hi>Cordelion</hi> in the Towres of Fame,</l>
                  <l>And with the dreadfull HENRIES of this land,</l>
                  <l>(Oh nev'r on earth did ſound a mightier name)</l>
                  <l>Thy meeker Image crown'd with Bayes ſhall ſtand:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then ſhall my Accents break with more ſucceſſe,</l>
                  <l>But now rude grief that no adornment beares</l>
                  <l>Smothers my notes, and bids me but expreſſe</l>
                  <l>A ſodaine ſorrow with my ſimple teares:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sufficeth me while thy ſweet Ghoſt doth ſleep,</l>
                  <l>Long ouer it with watry eyes to weep.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4168:12"/>
            <head>To the ſad houſhold of Prince HENRY.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IF vertue, goodnes, and a ſober life,</l>
               <l>If grauity, and wiſdome in yong yeeres,</l>
               <l>If a thrice honour'd ſtate, voide of all ſtrife</l>
               <l>And all good gifts that mans perfection bears,</l>
               <lg>
                  <l>Could but haue ſtopt the fatall hand of death,</l>
                  <l>Then worthy HENRY ſtill had drawn his breath.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe fleſh and Spirit diſioyn'd but for a time,</l>
               <l>With ſtedfaſt hope parted to meet againe,</l>
               <l>His heauenly parts vpwards to heauen do climbe;</l>
               <l>His earthly muſt a while in earth remaine,</l>
               <lg>
                  <l>Till death hath left to kill, and man to die,</l>
                  <l>And Time giuen place to all Eternitie.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fo ſo the Canon of eternall date,</l>
               <l>Hath praeordain'd (things bounded muſt obey)</l>
               <l>Vertue is an immortall eſtimate,</l>
               <l>Which neither Time nor Death can ouer-ſway</l>
               <lg>
                  <l>By her Prince HENRY liues; for vertues fame</l>
                  <l>Eterniſeth his memorable name.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4168:12"/>
               <l>Whoſe hope-full Age not come to Twenty yeares,</l>
               <l>In place of Honor and Authority.</l>
               <l>Did beare a burthen in the Countries cares,</l>
               <l>That gaue his name an happy Memory.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l>So iuſt, ſo wiſe, S'vpright in euery thing,</l>
                  <l>As ſtopt the venom of foule enuies ſting.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You that his friends and houſhould followers were,</l>
               <l>That ſaw the ſober cariage of his life:</l>
               <l>How he him ſelfe to all eſtates did beare,</l>
               <l>So Nobly minded, and ſo free from ſtrife.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh you and none ſo well, can ſound his praiſe,</l>
                  <l>That knew the vpright treadings of his waies.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I doe but ſound the Accents of Report,</l>
               <l>And ſure Report giues him a worthy name,</l>
               <l>That from his Cradle liu'd in vertues Court,</l>
               <l>Now free from change being regiſtred by fame.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l>Enioyes in heauen, heauens immortality,</l>
                  <l>And here on earth, earths happy Memory.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
